Dorothy C. Goodwin Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Dorothy C. Goodwin Papers.
undated, 1925-1993. [Bulk dates 1974-1992.]
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Goodwin, Dorothy C.
13 linear feet.
Dorothy C. Goodwin was born in Hartford, CT, on 2 September 1914. Goodwin grew up in Connecticut and graduated magna cum laude from Smith College in 1937 (B.A., Sociology). In 1974, Goodwin returned to government service by winning a seat in the Connecticut General Assembly as a Democratic representative of the 54th district (includes Mansfield). She held positions on the Education, Finance and Human Services Committees, and co-chaired the Education Committee for much of her career.
MSS19920036
Biography
Dorothy C. Goodwin led a diverse and distinguished life, one that included great accomplishments in academics and public service. She was born in Hartford, CT, on 2 September 1914 to Charles and Ruth Goodwin. Goodwin grew up in Connecticut and graduated magna cum laude from Smith College in 1937 (B.A., Sociology). She worked in the Bureau of Indian Affairs (1937-1939) and the Bureau of Agricultural Economics (1939-1942). Goodwin transferred to the Department of Economic Warfare and completed her wartime service in India. She attempted to enter the State Department upon her return from overseas, but alleged ties with Communists dogged her efforts. After a lengthy effort that ultimately cleared her of these charges, Goodwin was told that she was not sufficiently qualified for admission. She then proceeded to take part in the occupation of Japan as a government agricultural economist concerned with issues of land reform (1947-1951).
Goodwin left government service to begin graduate studies at the University of Connecticut, receiving the institution's first Ph.D. in agricultural economics (1957). She subsequently began a twenty-two year academic career at the University as a professor and assistant provost. During this period she published widely, particularly with respect to issues of state taxes and state aid to education.
In 1974, Goodwin returned to government service by winning a seat in the Connecticut General Assembly as a Democratic representative of the 54th district (includes Mansfield). She held positions on the Education, Finance and Human Services Committees, and co-chaired the Education Committee for much of her career. Goodwin's influence was crucial in designing new formulas for state educational aid to towns. She also figured prominently in the passage of the “Bottle Bill” and the adoption of programs to preserve agricultural land. Retiring from the House in 1984, she was appointed to the Connecticut State Board of Education by Governor William O'Neill and served in that position until 1990.
Scope and Content
The Goodwin papers contain correspondence, reports, publications, clippings, photographs, awards, and financial and political materials pertaining to the many careers of Dorothy C. Goodwin.
Arrangement
Series I: Political Papers ( 1969-1972 ) includes materials on Goodwin's five successful campaigns for the Connecticut House of Representatives and her involvement with the Mansfield Housing Committee. Also included are newspaper clippings concerning her political career, major issues of state politics and ephemeral materials pertaining to other Democratic candidates for state office.
Series II: Professional Papers ( 1940-1992 ) contains Goodwin's official reports on postwar land reform in Japan and many published articles and documents spanning her academic career at UConn. These materials are concerned, primarily, with the utilization of state tax revenues, modifications to the state tax system and education.
Series III: Personal Papers ( 1925-1993 ) houses a wide variety of personal and professional correspondence, reports, sketches, and information on the Goodwin family. Security statements prepared for the State Department in the 1940s to answer charges of Communist sympathies are found in Box 6. Also included are appointment calendars, college papers and a children's book she prepared.
Series IV: Awards ( undated, 1935-1992 ) contains degrees, certificates and plaques that recognize Goodwin's professional achievements, particularly in politics. The awards include several honorary law degrees from Connecticut universities, recognition from community groups and wards for legislative service.
Series V: Photographs ( undated, 1934-1991 ) includes photographs primarily from Goodwin's work with the Bureau of Indian Affairs and her overseas service in India and Japan. There are also photographs from her visit to China in 1947.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut politics. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Connecticut. State Board of Education.; Women—Connecticut—personal and other papers—20th century.; Agricultural economists—Connecticut.; Connecticut—Politics and governments—1951-; Connecticut—Education—Universities and colleges.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Personal Papers.; Manuscripts.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Videocassettes.
Occupations:
Educator.; Politician.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Ms. Goodwin to Historical Manuscripts and Archives (now Archives & Special Collections) of the University of Connecticut Libraries in 1992.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Political Papers, undated, 1969-1972
  - Campaign papers, 1974-1982 (Box 1:, Folder 1-12)
  - Campaign materials, undated, 1983-84 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Campaign buttons, undated (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - League of Women Voters—Mansfield, 1990 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - “An Act Implementing the Recommendations of the Governor's Commission on Higher Education and the Economy”, 1982 (Box 1:, Folder 16-18)
  - Friends of Dorothy Goodwin (financial), 1985 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Mansfield Housing Committee, 1969-1992 (Box 2:, Folder 20-22)
  - Newspaper clippings/articles, 1974-1986 (Box 2:, Folder 23-28)
  - Connecticut General Assembly directories, 1977-1980 (Box 2:, Folder 29)
- Series II: Professional Papers, 1940-1992
  - Yearbook of Agriculture— Appendix A, 1940 (Box 3:, Folder 30)
  - “A Place on Earth: A Critical Appraisal of Subsistence Homesteads”, 1942 (Box 3:, Folder 31)
  - “Project and Execution of Second Extension Work of Ogochi Reservoir Water System”, 1949 (Box 3:, Folder 32-33)
  - “Ryukyu Islands: Land Tenure Practices and Problems”, 1949 (Box 3:, Folder 34-35)
  - “On the Agricultural Credit Problem From the Standpoint of Present Farmers' Cooperative Associations”, c. 1949 (Box 3:, Folder 36-37)
  - “Japan's Agricultural Insurance System: A Statistical Description”, 1952 (Box 4:, Folder 38-39)
  - “Impact of State Participation in Financing of Education on Towns In Hartford County”, 1952 (Box 4:, Folder 40)
  - “Impact of State Participation in Town Highway Finance on Towns in Hartford County”, 1952 (Box 4:, Folder 41)
  - “The School Finance Problem in Connecticut”, 1954 (Box 4:, Folder 42)
  - “Five Years with the Japanese Occupation”, 1954 (Box 4:, Folder 43)
  - “Tax Problem of Connecticut School Expansion”, 1954 (Box 4:, Folder 44)
  - Untitled article for Oxford Bulletin, 1954 (Box 4:, Folder 45)
  - “The School Tax Crisis in Connecticut”, 1955 (Box 4:, Folder 46)
  - “Fiscal Needs and Capacity of Connecticut Towns”, 1956 (Box 4:, Folder 47)
  - Report to the Connecticut Commission on Agriculture, 1957 (Box 4:, Folder 48)
  - Dissertation: “State Grants and the Property Tax in Connecticut”, 1957 (Box 4:, Folder 49-52)
  - “State Grants and Property Tax Equalization in Connecticut”, 1957 (Box 4:, Folder 53)
  - “Suggested program of Economic Research and Extension for the Institute of Public Service, University of Connecticut”, 1957 (Box 4:, Folder 54)
  - “Blueprint for a Blueprint—The Booz, Allen and Hamilton Report”, 1960 (Box 4:, Folder 55)
  - “Some Approaches to the Problem of How to Distribute State Aid to Education”, 1961 (Box 4:, Folder 56)
  - “State Grants and Taxes”, 1961 (Box 4:, Folder 57)
  - “Connecticut's Tax Dilemma” (address), 1961 (Box 4:, Folder 58)
  - “Connecticut's Tax Problem: A Phony Dilemma?”, 1962 (Box 4:, Folder 59)
  - “Equalization as a Basis of State Aid”, 1963 (Box 4:, Folder 60)
  - “Do Equalization Grants for Education Equalize?”, 1963 (Box 5:, Folder 61)
  - “Connecticut's Tax Dilemma: What Choices Do We Have?”, 1969 (Box 5:, Folder 62)
  - “Statement in Support of a Progressive State Income Tax”, 1971 (Box 5:, Folder 63)
  - “Total Planning in Connecticut”, 1971 (Box 5:, Folder 64)
  - “The Coming Crisis in Education”, 1982 (Box 5:, Folder 65)
  - “White Horses Do Not Make Good Transportation”, 1988 (Box 5:, Folder 66)
  - “Principle vs. Compromise in the Legislative Process”, 1991 (Box 5:, Folder 67)
  - “Final Report—Commission to Effect Government Reorganization”, 1992 (Box 5:, Folder 68)
  - “The Coming Educational Crisis”, undated (Box 5:, Folder 69)
  - “The Guaranteed Tax Base Program for Financing Connecticut Public Schools: Is Full Funding Enough?”, undated (Box 5:, Folder 70)
  - “State Grants and Their Relation to Tax Burdens”, undated (Box 5:, Folder 71)
  - “The Last Battle”, undated (Box 5:, Folder 72)
- Series III: Personal Papers, 1925-1993
  - Education, 1928-1956 (Box 6:, Folder 73-75)
  - Talk on Irish Free State, 1931 (Box 6:, Folder 76)
  - Talk on Father Damien, c. 1931 (Box 6:, Folder 77)
  - Talk on J. M. Synge, 1933 (Box 6:, Folder 78)
  - Reviews for Smith College Weekly, 1934 (Box 6:, Folder 79)
  - “Noah Scovill and Samuel Colt: Two Contrasting Eras of American History”, 1936 (Box 6:, Folder 80)
  - Bureau of Indian Affairs, 1937-1938 (Box 6:, Folder 81-82)
  - Income Tax returns, 1939-1948 (Box 6:, Folder 83)
  - India, 1944-1945 (Box 6:, Folder 84-85)
  - Applications for federal employment, 1946-1951 (Box 6:, Folder 86-87)
  - Security statement, 1946-1947 (Box 6:, Folder 88-92)
  - “Submarginal Comfort Battalion”, 1946 (Box 6:, Folder 93)
  - Japanese occupation, undated, 1947-52 (Box 6:, Folder 94-96)
  - Résumés/curriculum vita, undated, 1956-57 (Box 6:, Folder 97)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1950 (Box 7:, Folder 98-119)
  - Correspondence, undated, 1951-92 (Box 8:, Folder 120-141)
  - Videotape—“Federal Tax Reform” League of Connecticut Women Voters, undated (Box 8:, Folder 142)
  - Videotape—“Dorothy Goodwin”, undated (Box 8:, Folder 143)
  - Chinese Hotel bills, 1948 (Box 8:, Folder 144)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated, 1961-93 (Box 9:, Folder 145-149)
  - Goodwin family, undated (Box 10:, Folder 150)
  - Home documents, 1963 (Box 10:, Folder 151)
  - Beck, Audrey, 1983 (Box 10:, Folder 152)
  - Chinese postcards, undated (Box 10:, Folder 153-155)
  - Taped speeches, 1984 (Box 10:, Folder 156)
  - Appointment calendars, 1959-1991 (Box 10:, Folder 157-175)
  - Unidentified materials, undated, 1945-86 (Box 10:, Folder 176-184)
  - Land surveys/drawings/plans for Dorothy Goodwin home on Browns Road, Mansfield, CT, 1963 (Box 11)
  - Sketches for children's book, undated (Box 12)
  - Sketches, undated
  - Map of Peiping, undated (Box 13)
  - Japanese posters on land reform, ca. 1948
- Series IV: Awards, undated, 1935-1992
  - Gift--Rear Admiral Chen Ming-Cheng, Director Taichung Harbor Bureau, Taiwan, undated (Box 14)
  - Gift--Taoyuan County Magistrate, Taiwan Province, China, undated (Box 14)
  - Placque--Minister Chu Mwei-Sen, Ministry of Education, China, undated (Box 14)
  - Certificate--General Headquarters, Allied Commander for Allied Powers, Pacific, 1951 (Box 14)
  - Certificate--University of Connecticut Alumni Association, Century Club, 1973-1974 (Box 14)
  - Certificate--University of Connecticut staff, 1974 (Box 14)
  - Placque--Northeastern COnnecticut Community Development Corporation, undated (Box 14)
  - Placques (2)--Boy Scouts of America, 1975 (Box 14)
  - Certificate--Phi Kappa Phi Honor Society, 1954 (Box 15)
  - Certificate--Gamma Sigma Delta Agricultural Honor Society, 1955 (Box 15)
  - Award--American Farm Economic Association, 1956 (Box 15)
  - Ph.D. University of Connecticut, 1957 (Box 15)
  - Certificate--State of Connecticut Tax Department course in Assessment Procedures, 1957 (Box 15)
  - Certificate--State of Connecticut Tax Department course in Advanced Assessment Procedures, 1958 (Box 15)
  - Membership--Omicron Delta Gamma, 1958 (Box 15)
  - Certificate--Election to General Assembly, 1975 (Box 15)
  - Award--ASPA Outstanding Legislator, 1978 (Box 15)
  - Award--Outstanding Legislator, Caucus of Connecticut Democrats, 1979 (Box 15)
  - Appointment, Connecticut Heritage Task Force, 1980 (Box 15)
  - Honorary Member, Delta Kappa Gamma Society, 1980 (Box 15)
  - Distingusihed Connecticut Citizen, UConn Alumni Association, 1980 (Box 15)
  - Silver Beaver Award, Citation--Boy Scouts of America, 1981 (Box 15)
  - Medal--Greater Hartford Chamber of Commerce, 1982 (Box 15)
  - Appreciation--State Department of Environmental Protection, 1983 (Box 15)
  - Connecticut State Assembly Membership, 1983 (Box 15)
  - Administration and Supervision Association, Southern Connecticut State University, 1984 (Box 15)
  - Award--Connecticut Federation of Democratic Women's Clubs, 1984 (Box 15)
  - Award--Connecticut State Board of Education, 1984 (Box 15)
  - Certificate--Phi Delta Kappa, 1984 (Box 15)
  - Resolution--Connecticut Association of Boards of Education, 1984 (Box 15)
  - Appointment--State Board of Education, 1985 (Box 16)
  - Award--Quinebaug Valley Community College, 1985 (Box 16)
  - Award--Board of Governors for Higher Education, 1985 (Box 16)
  - Award--Connecticut Valley Girl Scout Council, 1985 (Box 16)
  - Honorary Doctor of Laws--Connecticut College, 1986 (Box 16)
  - Award--Hartford College for Women, 1988 (Box 16)
  - Award--Connecituct State Board of Education, 1988 (Box 16)
  - Honorary Alumna--Dorothy C. Goodwin Elemnetary School, 1992 (Box 16)
  - Award--Connecticut Trails Council of Girl Scouts, 1992 (Box 16)
  - Presentation--Richard D. Tulisano, undated (Box 16)
  - Honorary Doctor of Laws--University of Hartford, 1982 (Box 17)
  - Honorary Doctor of Laws--Trinity College, 1983 (Box 17)
  - Citation--Connecticut General Assembly, 1984 (Box 17)
  - Honorary Doctor of Laws--Briarwood College, 1984 (Box 17)
  - Resolution--Connecticut Natural Gas Corporation, 1985 (Box 17)
  - Recognition--Phi Delta Kappa Fellow, 1985 (Box 17)
  - Award--Elementary and Middle School Principals' Association of Connecticut, 1983 (Box 17)
  - Award--United Social and Mental Health Services, Inc., undated (Box 17)
  - Award--Connecticut Library Association, 1981 (Box 17)
  - Award--Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights, 1980 (Box 17)
  - Award--Joshua's Trust, 1983 (Box 18)
  - Award--Contributions to the Humanities in Connecticut, 1991 (Box 18)
  - Resolution--United States Senate, 1992 (Box 18)
  - Award--National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Honorary Doctor of Laws--University of Connecticut, 1988 (Box 18)
  - Commencement Connecticut College, 1986 (Box 18)
  - Award--Association of Episcopal Colleges, 1985 (Box 18)
  - Certificate--Easter Seals, 1982 (Box 18)
  - American Civil Liberties Union Membership, 1974 (Box 18)
  - Placque--Japanese Minister of Agriculture and Forestry, 1952 (Box 18)
  - Placque--UConn Alumni Association, 1976 (Box 18)
  - Appreciation Award--Easter Seal Rehabilitation Center of Southeastern Connecticut, undated (Box 19)
  - Distinguished Alumni Award--University of Connecticut, 1982 (Box 19)
  - Citation--Connecticut General Assembly honoring service and induction into Mansfield Democratic Town Committee, 1989 (Box 20)
  - Distingusihed Alumni Award--Kingswood-Oxford School, 1983 (Box 20)
  - Placque--Asnuntuck Community College, 1980 (Box 20)
  - Citation--Connecticut General Assembly on dedication of Dorothy C. Goodwin Elementary School, 1992 (Box 20)
  - Diploma from Milton Academy, 1935 (Box 21)
  - Bachelor of Arts from Smith College, 1937 (Box 21)
  - Appreciation from NAACP, 1982 (Box 21)
- Series V: Photographs, undated, 1934-1991
  - Children at summer camp, 1934 (Box 22)
  - Bureau of Indian Affairs (13), 1937-1938 (Box 22)
  - Bureau of Indian Affairs (6), 1937-1938 (Box 23)
  - Milton Academy, 1938 (Box 23)
  - Dorothy C. Goodwin, 1940-1952 (Box 23)
  - India (6), 1944-1945 (Box 23)
  - Delegates from four nations draw for Japanese machine tools, 1947 (Box 23)
  - Japan, 1947-1952 (Box 23)
  - China trip, 1948 (Box 23)
  - Wedding of Asian couple, undated (Box 23)
  - Charles Goodwin residence (Hartford), 1948 (Box 23)
  - Charles Goodwin christening of boat, undated (Box 23)
  - Representative Dorothy C. Goodwin (2), 1975-1984 (Box 23)
  - Trinity College degree conferral, 1983 (Box 23)
  - U.S. Representative Sam Gejdenson, 1980s (Box 23)
  - Dorothy Goodwin and William O'Neill, 1985 (Box 23)
  - Rita Jaro's retirement, 1985 (Box 23)
  - Dorothy Goodwin roast, UConn FAculty-Alumni Center, 1985 (Box 23)
  - Honorary degree ceremony at UConn, 1988 (Box 23)
  - Wedding and family pictures, undated (Box 23)
  - Family property, undated (Box 23)
  - Unidentified, undated, 1991 (Box 23)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 24)